<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/">
    <channel>
        <title>Mural Blog</title>
        <link>https://www.getmural.io/blog</link>
        <description>Mural Blog</description>
        <lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</lastBuildDate>
        <docs>https://validator.w3.org/feed/docs/rss2.html</docs>
        <generator>https://github.com/jpmonette/feed</generator>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mural and Wordpress]]></title>
            <link>https://www.getmural.io/blog/2020/11/23/mural-and-wordpress</link>
            <guid>/2020/11/23/mural-and-wordpress</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[A question we get asked about on a fairly regular basis is "how on earth do I make Mural play nicely with Wordpress?"]]></description>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mural selected for Grant for the Web funding]]></title>
            <link>https://www.getmural.io/blog/2020/10/24/grant-for-the-web</link>
            <guid>/2020/10/24/grant-for-the-web</guid>
            <pubDate>Sat, 24 Oct 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Mural has been selected as a Mid Level Grantee in the Grant for the Web program, jointly administered by Mozilla, Creative Commons and Coil.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mural has been selected as a <a href="https://www.grantfortheweb.org/blog/2020-mid-grantees" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mid Level Grantee</a> in the <a href="https://www.grantfortheweb.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow noreferrer">Grant for the Web</a> program, jointly administered by Mozilla, Creative Commons and Coil.</p><p>Our project, titled &quot;Web Monetization in the Arts&quot; seeks to implement support for the emerging Web Monetization Protocol in Mural, as well as doing outreach work to people in the arts community. We also plan to greatly improve the Mural editor, as well as to implement various improvements as suggested by the Mural community (you can help by giving us feedback in the user survey on our <a href="/">homepage</a>).</p><p>What&#x27;s the <a href="https://webmonetization.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener nofollow noreferrer">Web Monetization Protocol</a>, you ask? It&#x27;s a new option to pay content creators for their work, while at the same time ensuring privacy for web consumers as they browse the web. With the Web Monetization Protocol, users will set up a &quot;wallet&quot; with a small amount of virtual currency. Then, as they browse compatible sites, a small amount is deducted from the user&#x27;s wallet and sent to the content creator.</p><p>Since its founding in 2017, Mural has always worked closely with people in the arts community. Especially as we face the pandemic together, we feel strongly that technologists and software developers need to work together with artists and other content creators to find new ways to be paid for their essential and vital work.</p><p>We&#x27;ll keep you posted on our progress here, in our social channels and subreddit.</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mural at Media Party 2020]]></title>
            <link>https://www.getmural.io/blog/2020/09/23/media-party-2020</link>
            <guid>/2020/09/23/media-party-2020</guid>
            <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Recently Mural was just at Media Party 2020 where our own Douglas Arellanes was holding the session Building visual stories without a CMS using Mural, while I was manning the chat answering all text based questions you had about Mural!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Recently Mural was just at <a href="https://mediaparty2020.sched.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Media Party 2020</a> where our own Douglas Arellanes was holding the session <a href="https://mediaparty2020.sched.com/event/drCY/construyendo-historias-visuales-sin-un-cms-usando-mural-building-visual-stories-without-a-cms-using-mural" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Building visual stories without a CMS using Mural</a>, while I was manning the chat answering all text based questions you had about Mural!</p><p>It was lovely to see the ~150 or so faces in the zoom session and perhaps countless others via Facebook live streaming! For those of you who are interested to catch the workshop or perhaps find the slides, you can <a href="https://www.facebook.com/hackshackersba/videos/978576952547745/?vh=e&amp;extid=NT0hVmLO4vlGGkxl" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">find the workshop streamed on Facebook</a> or <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1lvFCACO4LCVAZUYKxGPTewnFi-eqz5MdrJwwZbyPA0s/edit#slide=id.gcb9a0b074_1_0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">view the slides via Google Docs</a></p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="es" dir="ltr">Ya estamos en el <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Workshop?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Workshop</a> de Douglas Arellanes <a href="https://twitter.com/dougiegyro?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@dougiegyro</a> de Get Mural, en vivo desde Praga: &quot;Construyendo historias visuales sin un CMS usando Mural&quot; <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MediaParty?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#MediaParty</a>🎉<br/><br/>Pueden participar del taller acá 👇<a href="https://t.co/jJbyx7yk9p">https://t.co/jJbyx7yk9p</a> <a href="https://t.co/zeao3E14zV">pic.twitter.com/zeao3E14zV</a></p>— HacksHackersBA (@HacksHackersBA) <a href="https://twitter.com/HacksHackersBA/status/1306283491060051977?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">September 16, 2020</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charSet="utf-8"></script>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Mural at Mozfest 2019]]></title>
            <link>https://www.getmural.io/blog/2019/10/27/mozfest-2019</link>
            <guid>/2019/10/27/mozfest-2019</guid>
            <pubDate>Sun, 27 Oct 2019 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Mural's session Making open multimedia stories with Mural at Mozilla Festival 2019 was a lot of fun for us here at Mural. It was the first time Doug, Pete, and I had been together in the same room for ages!]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mural&#x27;s session <a href="https://discourse.mozilla.org/t/making-open-multimedia-stories-with-mural/46613" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Making open multimedia stories with Mural</a> at <a href="https://www.mozillafestival.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Mozilla Festival</a> 2019 was a lot of fun for us here at Mural. It was the first time Doug, Pete, and I had been together in the same room for ages!</p><p>The goal of our session was for participants to be able to build their own rich multimedia stories using available tools such as mobile phones, open source editing tools, and the Mural multimedia story tool. Doug opened up with an introduction to visual scrollytelling in the field of journalism, before we dove in to how to make your own visual stories using the Mural editing software.</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">My <a href="https://twitter.com/muralstories?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@muralstories</a> partners <a href="https://twitter.com/naomiaro?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@naomiaro</a> and <a href="https://twitter.com/PeteHaughie?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@PeteHaughie</a> I’m our <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/MozillaFestival?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#MozillaFestival</a> session on making multimedia stories with Mural. Here Naomi’s showing work in progress on the upcoming Mural 2! <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/Mozfest19?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#Mozfest19</a> <a href="https://t.co/IXVXlaH5k7">pic.twitter.com/IXVXlaH5k7</a></p>— Douglas Arellanes (@dougiegyro) <a href="https://twitter.com/dougiegyro/status/1188442479336525824?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">October 27, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charSet="utf-8"></script><p>I was showcasing the work on the new version of the Mural editor which will be much more responsive to your edits with the technology choices of <code>React</code> and <code>mobx-state-tree</code>. We are experimenting with a variety of ways to make creating your visual stories even easier - one of them being using open source image cropping and machine vision tools such as <a href="http://thumbor.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Thumbor</a>. The new editor is still in its early stages as we explore its direction here at Mural.</p><blockquote class="twitter-tweet"><p lang="en" dir="ltr">Thanks to <a href="https://twitter.com/EleonoreMayola?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@EleonoreMayola</a> I joined the <a href="https://twitter.com/muralstories?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@muralstories</a> session today. An awesome open source tool to create scrollable media-rich stories on the web. Thanks <a href="https://twitter.com/dougiegyro?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@dougiegyro</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/naomiaro?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@naomiaro</a> &amp; <a href="https://twitter.com/PeteHaughie?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">@PeteHaughie</a> <a href="https://twitter.com/hashtag/sketchnotes?src=hash&amp;amp;ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">#sketchnotes</a> <a href="https://t.co/wPTn8jm6Wl">pic.twitter.com/wPTn8jm6Wl</a></p>— Malwine (@malweene) <a href="https://twitter.com/malweene/status/1188453087498899456?ref_src=twsrc%5Etfw">October 27, 2019</a></blockquote> <script async="" src="https://platform.twitter.com/widgets.js" charSet="utf-8"></script><p>If you weren&#x27;t able to attend the session in London and would like to see what it was all about, you can <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1CuZomEmwQ3QqskSNZEYOrOeK0VFBwR1BHBFuIO7a0wE/edit#slide=id.gcb9a0b074_1_0" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">view the slides via Google Docs</a></p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[What We've Learned Making Mural]]></title>
            <link>https://www.getmural.io/blog/2018/06/04/what-we-learned</link>
            <guid>/2018/06/04/what-we-learned</guid>
            <pubDate>Mon, 04 Jun 2018 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Mural is a tool for creating visual longform stories. The Mural software is marking its official launch this week, and it’s been a pleasure to work on it as with the support of the Google Digital News Initiative’s Prototype Fund. As our project is open source (AGPL), we figured that it would be good to extend our transparency and share with you some of the things we’ve learned along the way.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Mural is a tool for creating visual longform stories. The <a href="https://www.getmural.io/">Mural software is marking its official launch this week</a>, and it’s been a pleasure to work on it as with the support of the Google Digital News Initiative’s Prototype Fund. As our project is open source (AGPL), we figured that it would be good to extend our transparency and share with you some of the things we’ve learned along the way.</p><p>A lot of this is technical, but as Father John Culkin once wrote about Marshall McLuhan’s philosophy, “We shape our tools, and thereafter they shape us.” The decisions we made in making Mural, and what we’ve learned in the process, might provide helpful insights for others making and using storytelling tools, as well as for those interested in how Mural was created.</p><p><img src="./assets/what-we-learned.jpeg" alt="Screenshot of Mural’s UI as of version 0.2.3"/></p><h3>Lesson 1: Get out of the CMS</h3><p>Traditional content management systems (CMSes) are great at a lot of things — they do a lot and do so stably. But one of the areas of greatest disappointment we’ve had has always been the way they work with visual content — the furthest most CMSes will go is to create a slideshow or embed media such as a video.</p><p>It’s 2018. We have cars that drive themselves, but the best visuals we get on web pages are slideshows. Something is wrong here.</p><p>We made Mural as a specific tool for a specific purpose: To present visual content with maximum impact. How we decided to achieve this turned out to be a very interesting exercise.</p><p>Mural had its start as a visual theme for a CMS called Newscoop, but to get it to work, users had to go through a great deal of pain. The CMS backend had to be hacked to within an inch of its life. Learning how to set up the server environment was a deeply Linux-heavy affair, and then users had to first learn the ins-and-outs of first the CMS, then the peculiarities of the theme. Users wailed and gnashed their teeth, but in the end they put up with it because the theme looked good once everything was in place.</p><p>The experience led to our first decision: In order to make a tool that truly works with visual content, we had to get away from the mentality that everything an organization does must be in one single CMS.</p><p>There are quite a few good CMS themes for outputting big visuals — Snowball for Wordpress is an example — but the problem isn’t with the theme, it’s with the backend. The Wordpress admin interface isn’t really isn’t made for working with visual content, and rearranging content can be tedious. This may change with initiatives like Wordpress’ Gutenberg editor — and we certainly hope so.</p><p>This led us to think: If we got away from the CMS, we could better understand the workflow of visual longform projects, which tend to be one-off efforts, assembled once and never updated again.</p><p>There was another plus. We could make the longform stories into static files, which would help to simplify things greatly on the technical side. With our output as static files, we wouldn’t need a dynamic server, with all of the overhead that managing one entails. In fact, we could go serverless if we wanted to. With static pages, organizations can publish their stories just about anywhere, and for less money and trouble than a CMS.</p><p>To be clear, strong visuals don’t require static pages. But static pages definitely makes the process simpler for less-technical users, and because time is money, we’re saving both.</p><p>It turns out we aren’t alone in thinking like this. The Chicago Tribune explored static HTML pages with its <a href="http://www.tarbell.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tarbell</a> project (a seriously underrated project, IMHO). The New York Times tends to hand-code its special pages, and the LA Times has its <a href="https://docs.google.com/presentation/d/1IybYcc0eVL-Rchm7lEQNwrM-AHRfr_M8ewfGYYNjeu8/edit?pli=1#slide=id.p" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Django Bakery</a> to generate static pages for its projects. You should check out the LA Times’ presentation on the Django Bakery to see what I mean. And then there’s <a href="https://jekyllrb.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Jekyll</a>, which is a whole universe unto itself.</p><p>All of these projects pointing to a similar conclusion: When it comes to visuals, it’s easier to go outside the CMS than to get it to do what you want, especially when it has to do with anything outside existing templates.</p><h3>Lesson 2: Focus on sequence</h3><p>We started to think about what a specialized tool would look like if it were built for the single purpose of making visual longforms. The task could be broken down to three components — assembling, sequencing and presenting, and we started to look for effective metaphors.</p><p>As it turns out, one of the metaphors that works relatively well is presentation software. There are <a href="https://www.bbc.com/news/technology-35038429" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">many faults to Powerpoint</a>, but one of the things it does very well is to help users lay out visual sequences. We liked the drag-and-drop metaphor they use for ordering screens, so that was our model. In our parlance, we call the workspace the Storyboard, and the individual components Items.
We also wanted a tool that would bring about a shift in how video is treated in web storytelling. Many have spoken of a pivot to video, and while that hype wave has crested, the need still remains for media organizations to come up with more compelling uses for video. We think that full-screen, user-driven, sequential video could provide storytellers with some new ways to tell those stories.
In this way, we have different Items for the type of content that’s being presented. There are currently two video items, three static image items, two slideshow items and one text item:</p><ul><li>Fullpage video</li><li>Background video</li><li>Image parallax</li><li>Image audio</li><li>Image background</li><li>Vertical slideshow</li><li>Horizontal slideshow</li><li>Centred text</li></ul><p>Each of these items can then be used to present content, and the sequence of items can be rearranged by dragging and dropping.
Lesson 3: Move to the desktop
When we started work on Mural, we originally intended it as server software. This would let us create a service for authoring content, and would let us use a centralized code base. But then we started thinking about the large amounts of files that would be used by such a service, and the storage and bandwidth implications of that, and we started to think otherwise. Also, there are still enough places in the world that don’t have cheap and plentiful wireless broadband for sending and working with video.</p><p>Luckily, there’s been tremendous progress on an open source project called <a href="https://www.electronjs.org" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Electron</a>, which lets developers create desktop apps using JavaScript, HTML and CSS, and the same code can be used on Mac, Windows and Linux. We considered having both desktop and server versions of Mural, but for now we’ve decided to concentrate on the desktop version, as it solves more of our users’ pain points:</p><ul><li><p><strong>Low barrier to entry</strong> You don’t need to know how to code to build a rich media site easily. Simply start writing and adding your media and the app will do the rest.</p></li><li><p><strong>It’s faster</strong> to work with a desktop program, because the user doesn’t have to upload videos to a server before working with the story</p></li><li><p><strong>It’s easier to make changes</strong> on the desktop version, as there is no lag</p></li><li><p>Because <strong>Mural outputs HTML, CSS and Javascript</strong>, technically-savvy users can make additional changes before uploading by working in your favorite coding environment. We’ve also discussed ways to support code insertion inside the Mural editor, so that a technically savvy user would be able to write (or copy) the code they need</p></li><li><p><strong>You have a choice of servers, and all of them are affordable.</strong> We’re using a mix of different servers for the stories we make with Mural, and all of them are quite affordable.</p></li><li><p><strong>Real world preview.</strong> This allows for believable previewing of your work because what you see is being rendered in an actual browser in real time as you work.</p></li><li><p><strong>Keep agile.</strong> The user can work on the go to build a story with their assets as they create them. No need to wait for phone signal and internet tethering to continue working.</p></li><li><p>The backend design we’ve chosen also lets us make a <strong>mobile app later on.</strong> We’d love to do this right away, but were faced with a very limited budget</p></li></ul><h3>Lesson 4: Simple things done well</h3><p>We understand very well that working with video, especially optimizing video, can take a long time. We had a lot of debates about whether or not to include video conversion functionality in the editor, but decided against this because it would add a lot of complexity to the code. Instead we decided to highlight in our manual a number of different external tools that are already very good at converting video. We would, however, like to make it clearer to the user that they have to optimize their videos themselves, and will improve this in future versions. That said, working with video is definitely an area we’re looking to improve.
We do plan on adding support to Mural for integrating YouTube and Vimeo videos in a future release, and are interested in embed support for a number of different services — support for data visualization tools like D3 are also on our to-do list. In fact, one of the artists we worked with in testing Mural, Dominic Smith, has created a piece, <a href="https://stories.getmural.io/isisarts/thevolunteers/">The Volunteers</a>, in which all of the videos are served from Vimeo.</p><h3>Lesson 5: Listening to and watching our users</h3><p>One of the reasons we made Mural was so that journalists and people working in the arts would have the ability to better convey arts stories, which by their very nature are multimedia. Some of our earliest testers are artists themselves, and they’ve used Mural both as a way to document their work and as an artistic medium in and of itself.</p><p>We’ve listened to our users very carefully and have also watched them use Mural, and this has given us much clearer prioritization of our bugs and feature requests. We’re big practitioners of Design Thinking, and we started the project with personae representing types of users, but over time these personae have been replaced with real users and their very real tasks, needs and pain points.
Design Thinking also helped us to clarify and refine Mural’s features and functionality, and we continue to follow its five primary steps: Empathize, Define, Ideate, Prototype and Test.</p><h3>Lesson 6: Trust the community</h3><p>One of our current discussions has to do with how to make Mural into a viable project that serves its community but also becomes a sustainable business. All of us on the Mural team are strong advocates of open source, and we’re taking a leap of faith in starting a new business while keeping that commitment. We believe that once we get Mural our into users’ hands, they’ll start to get involved in improving it and developing it further, as well as using the services we offer based on the tool.</p><p>We plan to offer a number of paid services on top of Mural, including hosting, optimization, and development of new features. We also want to offer consulting and training to show users how to make the most of not only Mural, but also a number of related apps and services. It’s cheesy to end this up this way, but it needs to be said: <a href="mailto:getinfo@getmural.io">Get in touch</a> and we can work together to make it easier to tell visual stories!</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
        <item>
            <title><![CDATA[Introducing Mural]]></title>
            <link>https://www.getmural.io/blog/2017/07/06/introducing-mural</link>
            <guid>/2017/07/06/introducing-mural</guid>
            <pubDate>Thu, 06 Jul 2017 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate>
            <description><![CDATA[Imagine the scene: Two friends, Douglas Arellanes, (that’s me) and Pete Haughie, are sitting in a bar on a Serbian mountaintop in April at 3am. They haven’t seen each other in person for several months but have been excitedly talking online about two new digital projects that had been making waves in the journalism and web design space for a long time already. After a few local pivo and rakija the gesticulation and conversational excitement starts to mount. “You know that New York Times thing? I reckon we could do that with our platform.” boasted Pete. “Oh yeah?” I challenged, “How long do you reckon that would take?” Pete’s beer sloshed over the side of his glass as he shrugged, “I dunno, six months maybe?”. I decided to call his bluff and gave him a retainer and some time. Six months to be precise.]]></description>
            <content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Imagine the scene: Two friends, Douglas Arellanes, (that’s me) and Pete Haughie, are sitting in a bar on a Serbian mountaintop in April at 3am. They haven’t seen each other in person for several months but have been excitedly talking online about two new digital projects that had been making waves in the journalism and web design space for a long time already. After a few local pivo and rakija the gesticulation and conversational excitement starts to mount. “You know that New York Times thing? I reckon we could do that with our platform.” boasted Pete. “Oh yeah?” I challenged, “How long do you reckon that would take?” Pete’s beer sloshed over the side of his glass as he shrugged, “I dunno, six months maybe?”. I decided to call his bluff and gave him a retainer and some time. Six months to be precise.</p><p><img src="./assets/introducing-mural.jpeg" alt="Great Eagle St London UK Mural"/></p><p>For quite some time, we’d been hearing that longform articles, and especially longform multimedia articles would be a crucial selling point for news organizations seeking to make their work stand out. The wave of hype surrounding projects like New York Times’ <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/projects/2012/snow-fall/index.html#/?part=tunnel-creek" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Snowfall</em></a> and <a href="http://www.nytimes.com/newsgraphics/2013/10/27/south-china-sea/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Shark and Minnow</em></a> and The Guardian’s <a href="https://www.theguardian.com/world/interactive/2013/may/26/firestorm-bushfire-dunalley-holmes-family" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>Firestorm</em></a> has come and gone, and it’s becoming fairly clear that only the biggest news organizations, with the technical capacity and budget to build multimedia projects from scratch, are able to do this on a regular basis. Some of the traditionally big digital players have tried with varying degrees of success to do longform digital media format. The BBC’s <a href="https://www.bbc.co.uk/news/resources/idt-sh/the_reykjavik_confessions" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer"><em>The Reykjavik Confessions</em></a> being a standout example of great content let down by less-than-great delivery.</p><p>Pete Haughie, Dominic Smith and I have been thinking about this for good long while now. When Pete and I worked together at <a href="https://www.sourcefabric.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Sourcefabric</a>, we were part of a team that worked on a project called <a href="http://storyteller-dev.lab.sourcefabric.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Storyteller</a>, which was initially nothing but a complicated theme for Newscoop, the CMS maintained by Sourcefabric. Storyteller had similar intentions, worked OK, and was used effectively by more than a few organizations, but it was soon clear to us that CMSes of any kind weren’t really well-suited to this kind of work — the backend had to be pretty severely abused in order to arrange the content in a way that would work for this purpose and editing and to say maintenance and publishing became difficult would be an understatement.</p><p>Many in the journalism/tech community have come to similar conclusions. A few years ago, I asked a data journalist what we as CMS makers could do to help their work. “Get the hell out of our way,” was the answer I got, and I couldn’t help but laugh at the truth she was telling. There are other interesting projects that have served as inspiration. The <a href="http://www.tarbell.io/" target="_blank" rel="noopener noreferrer">Tarbell</a> project, originally by the Chicago Tribune news applications team, was a really interesting model for us, as it was one of the first ‘NoCMS’ projects we’d seen. Tarbell makes it easy to publish static websites, which is useful especially in high-demand situations, as well as for situations where the content isn’t likely to be updated.</p><p>At the same time, we’re aware that although there are several very good services for hosting longform articles, we intend to improve on what they offer. We also aim to address a criticism made of many of the longform hosting services, to avoid ‘vendor lock-in’ and make it far easier for multimedia creators to export and transfer their work to other hosting providers and collaborators.
Unfortunately, due to a change in Sourcefabric’s focus, work on Storyteller effectively stopped in late 2015, but Pete and I continued to talk about what could be done to make it easier to create and publish longform multimedia. In the meantime independently and unbeknownst to us, Dominic Smith had been doing a lot of work using Storyteller to publish multimedia longform articles documenting art projects in the North of England as part of the EU-funded Corners of Europe project, and his hard work and pained entreaties has served as an inspiration to continue work on these tools with him working alongside us.</p><p>Dominic, Pete and I decided to apply for a prototype grant from the Google Digital News Innovation fund in its third round, and I’m happy to announce that as of today our project has been officially approved, so in coming weeks we will start work on a new project, which we are calling Mural, to create a new toolset to make it easier to make longform multimedia projects.
We’re looking forward to building Mural in the open, and as an open source project. While we have a number of ideas for what should be in the MVP version, we are also looking to partner with similarly-minded visual journalists, artists, storytellers, and developers. Please get in touch with us at <a href="mailto:info@getmural.io">info@getmural.io</a> and get involved!</p>]]></content:encoded>
        </item>
    </channel>
</rss>